# LEI ZHU, Ph.D.

Southern University of Science and Technology (SUSTech)
Taizhou Hall 429, 1088 Xueyuan Ave., Shenzhen, Guangdong, China 518055
<a href="https://www.acmrsg.org/zhu">https://www.acmrsg.org/zhu</a>

zhul3@sustech.edu.cn (+86) 0755-26601426

## **SCHOLARLY PROFILE**

My research goal is to better understand processes governing the distributions of atmospheric species, and their implications for air quality, public health, and climate. My research program combines **remote sensing**, **modeling**, and **data assimilation** techniques.

My **research interests** include: atmospheric chemistry and its implications, modeling of atmospheric chemistry, and observing trace gases from space.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

| 2019.12 – Present | Assistant Professor, Southern University of Science and Technology |
|-------------------|--|
| 2019.07 - 2019.12 | Research Scholar, Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics      |
| 2017.01 - 2019.07 | Post-doctoral Fellow, Harvard University                           |

## **EDUCATION**

| 2016.12 | Ph.D. in Environmental Science and Engineering, Harvard University |
|---------|--|
|         | Advisor: Prof. Daniel J. Jacob                                     |
| 2011.06 | MSci. in Environmental Science, Peking University                  |
|         | Advisor: Prof. Yu Song   |
| 2008.06 | B.S. in Environmental Science, Nankai University                   |

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

## First or corresponding author (\*)

- **Zhu, L.\***, G. González Abad, C. R. Nowlan, *et al.*: Validation of satellite formaldehyde (HCHO) retrievals using observations from 12 aircraft campaigns, *Atmos. Chem. Phys. Discuss.*, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-2019-1117, in review, 2020.
- **Zhu, L.\***, Jacob, D. J., Eastham, S. D., *et al.*: Effect of sea salt aerosol on tropospheric bromine chemistry, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 19, 6497-6507, 2019.
- **Zhu, L.\***, L. J. Mickley, D. J. Jacob *et al.*: Long-term (2005–2014) trends in formaldehyde (HCHO) columns across North America as seen by the OMI satellite instrument: Evidence of changing emissions of volatile organic compounds, *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, 44, 7079–7086, 2017.
- **Zhu, L.\***, D. J. Jacob, F. N. Keutsch *et al.*: Formaldehyde (HCHO) as a Hazardous Air Pollutant: Mapping surface air concentrations from satellite and inferring cancer risks in the United States, *Environ. Sci. Technol.*, 51, 5650–5657, 2017.
- **Zhu, L.\***, D. J. Jacob, P. S. Kim *et al.*: Observing atmospheric formaldehyde (HCHO) from space: validation and intercomparison of six retrievals from four satellites (OMI, GOME2A, GOME2B, OMPS) with SEAC<sup>4</sup>RS aircraft observations over the southeast US, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 16, 13477–13490, 2016.
- **Zhu, L.\***, D. J. Jacob, L. J. Mickley *et al.*: Anthropogenic emissions of highly reactive volatile organic compounds in eastern Texas inferred from oversampling of satellite (OMI) measurements of HCHO columns, *Environ. Res. Lett.*, 9, 114004, 2014.
- **Zhu, L.**, X. Huang, H. Shi *et al.*: Transport pathways and potential sources of PM<sub>10</sub> in Beijing, *Atmos. Environ.*, 45, 594–604, 2011.

### Co-authorship

Wang, X. et al. including L. Zhu: Direct links between hygroscopicity and mixing state of ambient aerosols: estimating particle hygroscopicity from their single-particle mass spectra, Atmos. Chem. Phys. 2020.

- Souri, A. et al. including L. Zhu: An Inversion of NOx and NMVOC Emissions using Satellite Observations during the KORUS-AQ Campaign and Implications for Surface Ozone over East Asia, Atmos. Chem. Phys. Discuss., 2020.
- Lu, X. et al. including L. Zhu: Development of the global atmospheric general circulation-chemistry model BCC-GEOS-Chem v1.0: model description and evaluation, Geosci. Model Dev., 2019.
- Chance, K. et al. including L. Zhu: TEMPO Green Paper; Chemistry, physics, and meteorology experiments with the Tropospheric Emissions: Monitoring of Pollution instrument, *Proc. SPIE* 11151, Sensors, Systems, and Next-Generation Satellites XXIII, 111510B (10 October 2019).
- Shen, L., D. J. Jacob, L. Zhu et al.: The 2005–2016 Trends of Formaldehyde Columns Over China Observed by Satellites: Increasing Anthropogenic Emissions of Volatile Organic Compounds and Decreasing Agricultural Fire Emissions, *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, 46, 2019.
- Zhang, Y. et al. including L. Zhu: Satellite-Observed Changes in Mexico's Offshore Gas Flaring Activity Linked to Oil/Gas Regulations, *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, 46, 1879–1888, 2019.
- Wang, X. et al. including L. Zhu: The role of chlorine in tropospheric chemistry, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 19, 3981–4003, 2019.
- Song, S. *et al.* including **L. Zhu**: Possible heterogeneous chemistry of hydroxymethanesulfonate (HMS) in northern China winter haze, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 19, 1357–1371, 2019.
- Sun, K., **Zhu, L**., K. Cady-Pereira *et al.*: A physics-based approach to oversample multi-satellite, multispecies observations to a common grid, *Atmos. Meas. Tech.*, 11, 6679–6701, 2018.
- Kaiser, J., D. J. Jacob, L. Zhu *et al.*: High-resolution inversion of OMI formaldehyde columns to quantify isoprene emission on ecosystem-relevant scales: application to the southeast US, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 18, 5483–5497, 2018.
- Miller, C. C. et al. including L. Zhu: Glyoxal yield from isoprene oxidation and relation to formaldehyde: chemical mechanism, constraints from SENEX aircraft observations, and interpretation of OMI satellite data, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 17, 8725–8738, 2017.
- Travis, K. R. *et al.* including **L. Zhu**: Why do models overestimate surface ozone in the Southeast United States?, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 16, 13561–13577, 2016.
- Fisher, J. A. *et al.* including **L. Zhu**: Organic nitrate chemistry and its implications for nitrogen budgets in an isoprene- and monoterpene-rich atmosphere: constraints from aircraft (SEAC<sup>4</sup>RS) and ground-based (SOAS) observations in the Southeast US, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 16, 5969–5991, 2016.
- Yu, K. *et al.* including **L. Zhu**: Sensitivity to grid resolution in the ability of a chemical transport model to simulate observed oxidant chemistry under high-isoprene conditions, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 16, 4369–4378, 2016.
- Marais, E. A. *et al.* including **L. Zhu**: Aqueous-phase mechanism for secondary organic aerosol formation from isoprene: application to the southeast United States and co-benefit of SO<sub>2</sub> emission controls, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 16, 1603–1618, 2016.
- Kim, P. S. *et al.* including **L. Zhu**: Sources, seasonality, and trends of southeast US aerosol: an integrated analysis of surface, aircraft, and satellite observations with the GEOS-Chem chemical transport model, *Atmos. Chem. Phys.*, 15, 10411–10433, 2015.
- Li, M., X. Huang, **L. Zhu** *et al.*: Analysis of the transport pathways and potential sources of PM<sub>10</sub> in Shanghai based on three methods, *Sci. Tot. Environ.*, 414, 525–534, 2012.
- Huang, X. et al. including **L. Zhu**: Mercury Emissions from Biomass Burning in China, *Environ. Sci. Technol.*, 45, 5650–5657, 2011.
- Song, Y. et al. including L. Zhu: A new emission inventory for nonagricultural open fires in Asia from 2000 to 2009, Environ. Res. Lett., 5, 014014, 2011.
- Wang, B., L. Zhu, Z. Gong et al.: Introduction to the methods of parameter estimation for environmental monitoring data set with truncated data below a detection limit, Acta Science Circumstantiae., 29,

1345–1350, 2009.

#### **AWARDS & GRANTS**

| Academic Recognition  |             |
|---|-------------|
| American Meteorological Society Special Award for OMI               | 2020        |
| Recognized reviewer for Atmospheric Pollution Research              | 2019        |
| NASA/DOI William T. Pecora Team Award for OMI                       | 2018        |
| Outstanding reviewer for Atmospheric Environment                    | 2017        |
| NASA Group Achievement Award for SEAC <sup>4</sup> RS               | 2015        |
| Graduate with honors, Nankai University                             | 2008        |
| Excellent All-round Student, Nankai University                      | 2005 - 2007 |
|   |             |
| Teaching  |             |
| Harvard University Certificate of Distinction in Teaching           | 2013        |
| •   |             |
| Fellowships   |             |
| Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory Visiting Scientist Fellowship | 2019        |
| Harvard Graduate Consortium on Energy and Environment Fellowship    | 2014 - 2016 |
| Graduate Scholarship, Peking University                             | 2008 - 2010 |
| Novozymes Fellowship  | 2007        |
| China National Educational Opportunity Grant                        | 2007        |
| Undergraduate scholarship, Nankai University                        | 2005 - 2006 |
|   |             |

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

#### **Talks**

Validation of satellite formaldehyde (HCHO) retrievals using observations from 12 aircraft campaigns, *AGU Fall Meeting*, 2019, San Francisco, CA, USA.

Satellite remote sensing of trace gases: principles, methods, and applications for air quality studies, *Atmospheric Chemistry Forum* (online), November 30, 2019 (invited).

Satellite remote sensing for air quality applications, with a focus on formaldehyde (HCHO), University of Illinois at Urbana–Champaign, Champaign, IL, 2019 (invited).

Satellite remote sensing for air quality applications, with a focus on formaldehyde (HCHO), Institute of Atmospheric Physics Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China, 2019, (invited).

Satellite remote sensing for air quality applications, with a focus on formaldehyde (HCHO), Peking University, Beijing, China, 2019 (invited).

Satellite remote sensing for air quality applications, with a focus on formaldehyde (HCHO), Southern University of Science and Technology, Shenzhen, China, 2019 (invited).

Modeling of tropospheric halogen (Cl-Br-I) chemistry: cycling, debromination, and impact, *The 1st Regional GEOS-Chem Asia Meeting*, Nanjing, China, 2018.

Mapping surface air concentrations from OMI and inferring cancer risks: implications for TEMPO, *TEMPO Science Meeting*, Cambridge, MA, 2017 (invited).

Observing atmospheric formaldehyde from space: validation, intercomparison, trend analysis and public health implications, *AGU Fall Meeting*, San Francisco, CA, 2016.

Observing atmospheric formaldehyde from space: Validation, intercomparison, trend analysis and public health implications, *Aura Science Meeting*, Rotterdam, The Netherlands, 2016.

Mapping of surface formaldehyde (HCHO) from space for air quality management, *The 9<sup>th</sup> NASA Air Quality Applied Sciences Team Meeting*, St. Louis University, St. Louis, MO, 2015.

Indirect validation of new OMI, GOME-2B and OMPS formaldehyde retrievals using SEAC<sup>4</sup>RS data, *The 7th International Conference of GEOS-Chem*, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, 2015.

Validation of satellite HCHO observations (OMI, GOME-2B, OMPS) using SEAC4RS data, SEAC4RS

- Science Meeting, Caltech, Pasadena, CA, 2015.
- Anthropogenic emissions of highly reactive volatile organic compounds inferred from oversampling of OMI HCHO columns, *EOS Aura Science Team Meeting 10<sup>th</sup> year anniversary celebration*, College Park, MD, 2014.
- Anthropogenic emissions of highly reactive VOCs (HRVOCs) inferred from oversampling of OMI formaldehyde columns, *The 6<sup>th</sup> NASA Air Quality Applied Sciences Team Meeting*, Rice University, Houston, TX, 2014.
- Math in Nature: finding order in chaos, at Harvard Medical School, *Science in News*, Boston, MA, 2013 (invited).
- Variability of HCHO over the United States: Implications for VOCs Emissions, *The 5<sup>th</sup> NASA Air Quality Applied Sciences Team Meeting*, University of Maryland, College Park, MD, 2013.
- A spike in electricity demand due to severe summer heatwaves: Increase of SO<sub>2</sub> emissions detected from space, *The 18th Seminar of JSPS-MOE Core University Program*, Beijing, China, 2010.
- Estimating of fire emissions in Boreal Siberia by satellite data sets, *The 6<sup>th</sup> Seminar of Environment Modeling and Pollution Controlling*, Beijing, China, 2009.

#### **Posters**

- Validation of satellite formaldehyde (HCHO) retrievals using aircraft observations and implication for TEMPO, *TEMPO Science Meeting*, University of Wisconsin–Madison, WI, 2019.
- Effect of sea-salt aerosol on tropospheric bromine chemistry, *The 9<sup>th</sup> International Conference of GEOS-Chem*, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, 2019.
- Effect of sea-salt aerosol on tropospheric bromine chemistry, *AGU Fall Meeting*, Washington, D.C., 2018. Observing atmospheric formaldehyde from space: trend analysis and public health implications, *The 8<sup>th</sup> International GEOS-Chem Meeting*, Cambridge, MA, 2017.
- Validation of satellite HCHO retrievals with aircraft (SEAC<sup>4</sup>RS) observations, *Atmospheric Radiation Workshop*, NCAR, Boulder, CO, 2016.
- Anthropogenic emissions of highly reactive volatile organic compounds inferred from oversampling of OMI HCHO columns, *AGU Fall Meeting*, San Francisco, CA, 2014.
- Indirect validation of GOME-2/MetOp-A and B formaldehyde retrievals using SEAC<sup>4</sup>RS data: Preliminary results, *The 7<sup>th</sup> NASA Air Quality Applied Sciences Team Meeting*, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, 2014.
- Indirect Validation of GOME-2/MetOp-A and B and New OMI formaldehyde (HCHO) retrievals using SEAC<sup>4</sup>RS data: Preliminary results, *SEAC<sup>4</sup>RS Science Meeting*, NIST, Boulder, CO, 2014.
- Variability of HCHO over the Southeastern United States observed from space: Implications for VOC emissions, *AGU Fall Meeting*, San Francisco, CA, 2012.
- Spikes in electricity demand during severe summer heat waves: Increased SO<sub>2</sub> emissions detected from space, *AGU Fall Meeting*, San Francisco, CA, 2010.

# **TEACHING & ADVISING EXPERIENCE**

# **Teaching Assistant**

Lab demonstrations/tutoring, grading, exam grading, offering weekly sections

- o Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics, Graduate course, Harvard University, 12 students, 2017.
- o *The Fluid Earth: Oceans, Atmosphere, and Climate*, Undergraduate course, Harvard University, 50 students, 2013.

## **Advising Experience**

- o 3 Undergraduate students
- o 2 Graduate students

## PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

# **Committee Experience**

| GEMS Science Team Member                                      | 2019 -      |
|---|-------------|
| OMPS (NPP and NOAA-20) Science Team Member                    | 2018 -      |
| TEMPO Science Team Member                                     | 2017 -      |
| NASA Aura Science Team Member                                 | 2016 -      |
| Chair of weekly Harvard Atmospheric Sciences seminar series   | 2016 - 2017 |
| NASA SEAC <sup>4</sup> RS Flight Campaign Science Team Member | 2012 - 2015 |
| NASA Air Quality Applied Sciences Team Member                 | 2011 - 2015 |

# **Guest Editor**

Remote Sensing

# **Peer Review Journals**

Atmosphere, Atmospheric Environment, Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics, Atmospheric Measurement Techniques, Atmospheric Pollution Research, Environmental Science & Technology, Geophysical Research Letters, Journal of Geophysical Research, Nature Climate Change, Remote Sensing

Last updated: Aug. 01, 2020